<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.ericloucks.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.ericloucks.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-05-02T13:06:48-04:00</updated><id>https://blog.ericloucks.com/</id><title type="html">The Back of My Mind</title><subtitle>The random blog of Eric Loucks</subtitle><author><name>Eric Loucks</name><email>me@ericloucks.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Setting the Stage</title><link href="https://blog.ericloucks.com/2019-02-13/setting-the-stage" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Setting the Stage" /><published>2019-02-13T18:07:24-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-13T18:07:24-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.ericloucks.com/2019-02-13/setting-the-stage</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.ericloucks.com/2019-02-13/setting-the-stage">&lt;p&gt;It is never more apparent to me how imperfect language is as a communication medium than when I attempt to convey my deepest thoughts in writing. I find thoughts to be abstract, parallel, and multifaceted by nature, whereas words require specificity and singularity. With words, you maintain one line of thinking at a time, maybe two or three if you are &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; talented. But there are thoughts that can only be clear in the storm of the mind. There are intangible ideas that have their shadow cast in words, but not their substance, and concepts you can only dance around with words, never naming them. It is for these reasons, I hold a small fear of writing. It is difficult to do well, and if done poorly, it inevitably leads to misunderstandings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The devil is in the details. It is simple to convey some things with language. The cat ran. The glass is cracked. Sentences such as those are easily understood, but they also leave much unsaid. I might infer that the glass that is cracked is clear, but in reality it is red and opaque. Even if these characteristics are spelled out in the sentence, even if I go way overboard on explaining the state of the glass in detail – The opaque, red glass, which is cylindrical but tapers into a square at the bottom, has a thin, snaking crack from the lip, running about half-way down. – there is still so much about it that the reader is left to fill in. Not to mention the sentence &lt;em&gt;sounds&lt;/em&gt; awful. I think most writers would argue that having the reader infer details is a great thing. After all, the best stories are thick with metaphors and abstract descriptions. The adage “less is more” rings true in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concepts are even worse, in that they are non-physical. They pose a challenge because you can only attempt to convey them by either referencing a physical example or utilizing other, more well-known ideas. Love, one of the most iconic abstract feelings, is an excellent example. You can give examples of acts that demonstrate it, you can give any number of metaphors for it, but none of that tells you what it truly is. People tend to approach some consensus about the idea over time, and forget to question its nature. Personally, I find that maddening. How am I to know my concept of love is the same as yours? I can’t. &lt;strong&gt;Ever&lt;/strong&gt;. We have words, and they can be used to explain ideas, but never with perfect accuracy. At the end of the day, words mean different things to different people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t mean to disparage language. It is wonderful, and without it, we would surely be lost as a species. I do intend to point out how difficult it is to use well. I have essentially spent three paragraphs trying to convey the concept “words are hard,” and I’m still not sure I captured why. If that is not irony, I don’t know what is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the thoughts I am most interested in discussing in this blog, those I find most rewarding to discuss, are those same abstract, complicated ones I have a challenging time writing about.  At the end of the day, I don’t have confidence that I will do these ideas justice in my explanations. I am limited by my own skill as a writer. Having said that, I will certainly give it a go, and I hope you might be patient with me as I attempt to write through the thematic incoherence that this blog will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you hate long-winded explanations like the one above, this blog is not for you. This is my style. I am not brave enough to give short explanations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Eric Loucks</name><email>me@ericloucks.com</email></author><summary type="html">It is never more apparent to me how imperfect language is as a communication medium than when I attempt to convey my deepest thoughts in writing. I find thoughts to be abstract, parallel, and multifaceted by nature, whereas words require specificity and singularity. With words, you maintain one line of thinking at a time, maybe two or three if you are very talented. But there are thoughts that can only be clear in the storm of the mind. There are intangible ideas that have their shadow cast in words, but not their substance, and concepts you can only dance around with words, never naming them. It is for these reasons, I hold a small fear of writing. It is difficult to do well, and if done poorly, it inevitably leads to misunderstandings.</summary></entry></feed>